who were responsible for its well-being. He fixed roads, he mended wetlands, he did some anti-poaching. And then one day we were out together, and he came across the tracks of where a female leopard had walked. And it was an old track, but for fun he turned and he began to follow it, and I tell you, I could tell by the speed at which he moved on those pad marks that this man was a Ph.D.-level tracker. If you drove past Solly somewhere out on the reserve, you look up in your rearview mirror, you'd see he'd stopped the car 20, 50 meters down the road just in case you need help with something. The only accusation I ever heard leveled at him was when one of our clients said, "Solly, you are pathologically helpful." (Laughter) When I started professionally guiding people out into this environment, Solly was my tracker. We worked together as a team. And the first guests we ever got were a philanthropy group from your East Coast, and they said to Solly, on the side, they said, "Before we even go out to see lions and leopards, we want to see where you live." So we took them up to his house, and this visit of the philanthropist to his house coincided with a time when Solly's wife, who was learning English, was going through a phase where she would open the door by saying, "Hello, I love you. Welcome, I love you." (Laughter) And there was something so beautifully African about it to me, this small house with a huge heart in it. Now on the day that Solly saved my life, he was already my hero. It was a hot day, and we found ourselves down by the river. Because of the heat, I took my shoes off, and I rolled up my pants, and I walked into the water. Solly remained on the bank. The water was clear running over sand, and we turned and we began to make our way upstream. And a few meters ahead of us, there was a place where a tree had fallen out of the bank, and its branches were touching the water, and it was shadowy. And if had been a horror movie, people in the audience would have started saying, "Don't go in there. Don't go in there." (Laughter) And of course, the crocodile was in the shadows. Now the first thing that you notice when a crocodile hits you is the ferocity of the bite. Wham! It hits me by my right leg. It pulls me. It turns. I throw my hand up. I'm able to grab a branch. It's shaking me violently. It's a very strange sensation having another creature try and eat you, and there are few things that promote vegetarianism like that. (Laughter) Solly on the bank sees that I'm in trouble. He turns. He begins to make his way to me. The croc again continues to shake me. It goes to bite me a second time. I notice a slick of blood in the water around me that gets washed downstream. As it bites the second time, I kick. My foot goes down its throat. It spits me out. I pull myself up into the branches, and as I come out of the water, I look over my shoulder. My leg from the knee down is mangled beyond description. The bone is cracked. The meat is torn up. I make an instant decision that I'll never look at that again. As I come out of the water, Solly arrives at a deep section, a channel between us. He knows, he sees the state of my leg, he knows that between him and I there is a crocodile, and I can tell you this man doesn't slow down for one second. He comes straight into the channel. He wades in to above his waist. He gets to me. He grabs me. I'm still in a vulnerable position. He picks me and puts me on his shoulder. This is the other thing about Solly, he's freakishly strong. He turns. He walks me up the bank. He lays me down. He pulls his shirt off. He wraps it around my leg, picks me up a second time, walks me to a vehicle, and he's able to get me to medical attention. And I survive. Now — (Applause) Now I don't know how many people you know that go into a deep channel of water that they know has a crocodile in it to come and help you, but for Solly, it was as natural as breathing. And he is one amazing example of what I have experienced all over Africa. In a more collective society, we realize from the inside that our own well-being is deeply tied to the well-being of others. Danger is shared. Pain is shared. Joy is shared. Achievement is shared. Houses are shared. Food is shared. Ubuntu asks us to open our hearts and to share, and what Solly taught me that day is the essence of this value, his animated, empathetic action in every moment. Now although the root word is about people, I thought that maybe ubuntu was only about people. And then I met this young lady. Her name was Elvis. In fact, Solly gave her the name Elvis because he said she walked like she was doing the Elvis the pelvis dance. She was born with very badly deformed back legs and pelvis. She arrived at our reserve from a reserve east of us on her migratory route. When I first saw her, I thought she would be dead in a matter of days. And yet, for the next five years she returned in the winter months. And we would be so excited to be out in the bush and to come across this unusual track. It looked like an inverted bracket, and we would drop whatever we were doing and we would follow, and then we would come around the corner, and there she would be with her herd. And that outpouring of emotion from people on our safari trucks as they saw her, it was this sense of kinship. And it reminded me that even people who grow up in cities feel a natural connection with the natural world and with animals. And yet still I remained amazed that she was surviving. And then one day we came across them at this small water hole. It was sort of a hollow in the ground. And I watched as the matriarch drank, and then she turned in that beautiful slow motion of elephants, looks like the arm in motion, and she began to make her way up the steep bank. The rest of the herd turned and began to follow. And I watched young Elvis begin to psych herself up for the hill. She got visibly -- ears came forward, she had a full go of it and halfway up, her legs gave way, and she fell backwards. She attempted it a second time, and again, halfway up, she fell backwards. And on the third attempt, an amazing thing happened. Halfway up the bank, a young teenage elephant came in behind her, and he propped his trunk underneath her, and he began to shovel her up the bank. And it occurred to me that the rest of the herd was in fact looking after this young elephant. The next day I watched again as the matriarch broke a branch and she would put it in her mouth, and then she would break a second one and drop it on the ground. And a consensus developed between all of us who were guiding people in that area that that herd was in fact moving slower to accommodate that elephant. What Elvis and the herd taught me caused me to expand my definition of ubuntu, and I believe that in the cathedral of the wild, we get to see the most beautiful parts of ourselves reflected back at us. And it is not only through other people that we get to experience our humanity but through all the creatures that live on this planet. If Africa has a gift to share, it's a gift of a more collective society. And while it's true that ubuntu is an African idea, what I see is the essence of that value being invented here. Thank you. (Applause) Pat Mitchell: So Boyd, we know that you knew President Mandela from early childhood and that you heard the news as we all did today, and deeply distraught and know the tragic loss that it is to the world. But I just wondered if you wanted to share any additional thoughts, because we know that you heard that news just before coming in to do this session. Boyd Varty: Well thanks, Pat. I'm so happy because it was time for him to pass on. He was suffering. And so of course there's the mixed emotions. But I just think of so many occurrences like the time he went on the Oprah show and asked her what the show would be about. (Laughter) And she was like, "Well, it'll be about you." I mean, that's just incredible humility. (Laughter) He was the father of our nation and we've got a road to walk in South Africa. And everything, they used to call it Madiba magic. You know, he used to go to a rugby match and we would win. Anywhere he went, things went well. But I think that magic will be with us, and the important thing is that we carry what he stood for. And so that's what I'm going to try and do, and that's what people all over South Africa are trying to do. PM: And that's what you've done today. BV: Oh, thank you. PM: Thank you. BV: Thank you. Thanks very much. (Applause)
responsables de su bienestar. Arregló caminos, mejoró los humedales, algo de anti caza furtiva. Y un día salimos juntos y se encontró con las huellas de una leopardo hembra. Y eran rastros antiguos, pero para divertirse se volvió y comenzó a seguirlos, y les digo, supe por la velocidad con la que se movía por esas marcas de almohadillas, que este hombre era un rastreador de nivel doctorado. Si pasabas a Solly en algún lugar fuera de la reserva, al mirar por el retrovisor verías que había parado el coche 20, 50 metros atrás de la carretera por si acaso necesitabas ayuda con algo. La única acusación que escuché hacía él fue cuando uno de nuestros clientes dijo: "Solly, eres patológicamente servicial". (Risas) Cuando empecé profesionalmente a ser guía en este ambiente, Solly fue mi rastreador. Trabajamos juntos como un equipo. Y los primeros invitados que tuvimos fue un grupo filantrópico de la Costa Este, y le dijeron a Solly, de lado, dijeron: "Antes de ni siquiera salir a ver los leones y leopardos, queremos ver dónde vives". Así que los llevamos hasta su casa, y esta visita de los filántropos a su casa coincidió con un momento en que la esposa de Solly, que estaba aprendiendo inglés, estaba pasando por una etapa donde abría la puerta diciendo: "Hola, te amo. Bienvenido, te amo". (Risas) Y había algo tan maravillosamente africano en esto para mí, esta pequeña casa con un gran corazón en ella. Ahora, el día en que Solly salvó mi vida, ya era mi héroe. Era un día caluroso, y nos encontramos abajo en el río. Por del calor, me quité los zapatos, y me enrollé los pantalones, y caminé dentro del agua. Solly permaneció en la ribera. El agua era clara corriendo sobre arena, nos desviamos y comenzamos a subir aguas arriba. Y a pocos metros delante de nosotros, había un lugar donde había caído un árbol de la ribera, y sus ramas estaban tocando el agua, y estaba sombrío. Y si hubiera sido una película de terror, la gente del público habría empezado a decir: "No entres. No vayas". (Risas) Y por supuesto, el cocodrilo estaba en las sombras. Lo primero que ves cuando te golpea un cocodrilo es la ferocidad de la mordedura. ¡Zas! Me di cuenta por mi pierna derecha. Me tira. Se volteó. Lance mi mano hacia arriba, pude agarrar una rama. Me revuelve violentamente. Es una sensación muy extraña tener otra criatura que quiere comerte y hay pocas cosas que promuevan el vegetarianismo más que esa. (Risas) Solly en la ribera ve que tengo problemas. Se vuelve, se aproxima hacia mí. El cocodrilo continúa otra vez batiéndome. Va a morder una segunda vez. Noté una mancha de sangre en el agua alrededor mío que se desvanecía aguas abajo. Al morderme por segunda vez, pateo. Mi pie va hondo en su garganta. Me escupe hacia fuera. Me levanto agarrándome de unas ramas y cuando salgo del agua, miro sobre mi hombro. Mi pierna de la rodilla hacia abajo está destrozada más allá de toda descripción. El hueso está roto. La carne desgarrada. Tomé la decisión instantánea de nunca mirar eso otra vez. Al salir del agua, Solly llegó a una parte profunda, un canal entre nosotros. Él sabe, ve el estado de mi pierna, sabe que entre él y yo hay un cocodrilo, y puedo decir que este hombre no paró ni un segundo. Entró directamente en el canal. Se hundió arriba de su cintura. Llegó a mí. Me agarró. Todavía estoy en una posición vulnerable. Me carga y me pone sobre sus hombros. Esta es otra cosa sobre Solly, es monstruosamente fuerte. Se vuelve. Me saca a la ribera. Me pone en el suelo. Se quita su camisa. La envuelve alrededor de mi pierna, me carga por segunda vez, me lleva a un vehículo, y es capaz de conseguirme atención médica. Y sobreviví. Ahora —aplausos— Ahora no sé cuánta gente conocen capaz de entrar en un canal profundo de agua que saben que hay un cocodrilo para ir en su ayuda, pero para Solly, era tan natural como respirar. Y es un ejemplo sorprendente de lo que he experimentado por toda el África. En una sociedad más colectiva, nos damos cuenta desde el interior que nuestro bienestar está profundamente ligado al bienestar de los demás. Se comparte el peligro. Se comparte el dolor. Se comparte la alegría. Se comparte el logro. Se comparten las casas. Se comparte la comida. Ubuntu nos pide que abramos nuestros corazones y compartamos, y lo que me enseñó Solly ese día es la esencia de este valor, su acción animada, empática en cada momento. Ahora aunque la raíz de la palabra es sobre la gente, pensé que tal vez ubuntu era solo sobre la gente. Y entonces conocí a esta joven. Su nombre era Elvis. De hecho, Solly le dio el nombre de Elvis porque dijo que caminaba como hacía Elvis el baile de la pelvis. Nació con patas traseras y la pelvis seriamente deformadas. Llegó a nuestra reserva de una reserva al este de la nuestra en su ruta migratoria. Cuando la vi por primera vez, pensé que moriría en cuestión de días. Y sin embargo, en los 5 años siguientes regresaba en los meses de invierno. Y nos emocionaríamos mucho de estar fuera en la selva y encontrar esta pista inusual. Parecía un soporte invertido, y pararíamos lo que estuviéramos haciendo y la seguiríamos, y luego llegaríamos a la vuelta de la esquina, y ahí estaría con su manada. Y ese torrente de emociones de las personas en nuestros camiones safari al verla, fue este sentido de afinidad. Y me recordó que incluso las personas que crecen en las ciudades sienten una conexión natural con el mundo natural y con los animales. Y aún sigo sorprendido de que ella haya sobrevivido. Un día llegamos a ellos en este pequeño abrevadero. Era una especie de hueco en el suelo. Y observé como la matriarca bebió, y luego volvió con ese hermoso movimiento lento de los elefantes, que parece como un brazo en movimiento, y ella comenzó ir hasta el borde escarpado. El resto de la manada se volvió y comenzó a seguir. Y vi a la joven Elvis comenzar a ponerse nerviosa por subir la colina. Era visible, las orejas hacia adelante, tenía que subir y estaba a mitad de camino, sus piernas cedieron y cayó hacia atrás. Lo intentó una segunda vez, y una vez más, a medio camino, cayó de espaldas. Y en el tercer intento, algo increíble sucedió. A mitad de camino hasta la ribera, un elefante joven adolescente vino detrás de ella, y apoyó su tronco debajo de ella, y empezó a sacarla hacia la ribera. Y se me ocurrió que el resto de la manada de hecho estaba cuidando esta elefante joven. Al día siguiente vi otra vez como la matriarca rompió una rama y se lo puso en su boca, y luego rompió una segunda y la puso en el suelo. Y un consenso de todos nosotros los que guiamos personas en esa zona es que esa manada de hecho se movía despacio para dar cabida a esa elefante. Lo que Elvis y la manada me enseñaron me llevó a ampliar mi definición de ubuntu, y creo que en la catedral de la naturaleza, vamos a ver las partes más hermosas de nosotros mismos reflejadas hacia nosotros. Y no es solo a través de otras personas que podamos experimentar nuestra humanidad sino a través de todas las criaturas que viven en este planeta. Si África tiene un don para compartir, es el regalo de una sociedad más colectiva. Y si bien es cierto que ubuntu es una idea africana, lo que veo es la esencia de ese valor que se inventó aquí. Gracias. (Aplausos) Pat Mitchell: Boyd, sabemos que tú conociste al presidente Mandela en tu primera infancia y que oíste la noticia como todos lo hicimos hoy, y que te afecta profundamente y sabemos la trágica pérdida que es para el mundo. Pero me preguntaba si quisieras compartir algún pensamiento adicional, porque sabemos que oíste la noticia justo antes de venir a esta sesión. Boyd Varty: Bueno gracias, Pat. Estoy muy feliz porque ya era hora de que él descansara. Estaba sufriendo. Y por supuesto hay emociones mezcladas. Pero pienso en tantas ocurrencias como cuando fue al show de Oprah y le preguntó que sobre que sería el programa. (Risas) Y era como, "Bueno, será sobre Usted". Es decir, es simplemente una increíble humildad. (Risas) Él fue el padre de nuestra nación y tenemos un camino por recorrer en Sudáfrica. Y todo, solían llamarle la magia Madiba. Saben, solía ir a un partido de rugby y ganaríamos. A cualquier lugar que fuera, las cosas salían bien. Pero creo que la magia estará con nosotros, y lo importante es que llevamos lo que él representaba. Y eso es lo que voy a intentar y hacer, y eso es lo que intentan hacer personas en toda Sudáfrica. PM: Y eso es lo que has hecho hoy. BV: Gracias. PM: Gracias. BV: Gracias. Muchísimas gracias. (Aplausos)